<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<marinduque>
<stacruz>
 
  <title>STA.CRUZ</title>
 
 <welcome>WELCOME AND VISIT STA.CRUZ !!!</welcome>
 
 <maniwaya>
 
 <title>maniwaya</title>
 
  <description><l1>Located in the town of Santa Cruz in Marinduque, Maniwaya Island is one of the most popular islands in the province. It is situated in the middle of Polo Island and Mompong Island. People often flock to Maniwaya to see and enjoy the white sand beaches. Its southwest and northeast sides both boast a kilometer stretch of shoreline. The southwest side is home to affordable accommodations and water activities like snorkeling and free diving. The northeast side of Maniwaya is where Palad Sandbar can be found. Because of its prime location, the island also offers stunning sunrise and sunset views. </l1>

  </description>
 
 </maniwaya>

 <polo>
  <title>polo</title>

  <description><l1>Polo is a barangay in the municipality of Santa Cruz, in the province of Marinduque. Its population as determined by the 2020 Census was 845. This represented 1.55% of the total population of Santa Cruz.</l1>
  
  </description>
 </polo>

 <mongpong>
  <title>mongpong</title>

  <description><l1>Mongpong Island has a vast stretch of white beach facing southwest and northwest. The sand is a mixture of fine to coarse. I won’t lie and tell people that the beach is creamy white sand tapos pagdating nila hindi naman, hindi naman ako nambubudol. But what I really like about Mongpong is its clean coastal area, few to no people swimming around (which you could actually own the entire beach), and the turquoise crystal clear waters surrounding the island. </l1>
  
  </description>
 </mongpong>

 <lapresa>
  <title>lapresa</title>

  <description><l1>It’s not in Baguio, but it’s in Brgy. Taytay, Santa Cruz, Marinduque. A high hill where, when you reach the top, you can see the surrounding area, a small spot of the sea, and it feels like you’re in New Zealand. The best times to visit are during sunrise and sunset. </l1>
  
  </description>
 </lapresa>

</stacruz>

<mogpog>
  <title>MOGPOG</title>
 
 <welcome>WELCOME AND VISIT MOGPOG !!!</welcome>

 <viewdeck>
 
 <title>viewdeck</title>

 <description><l1>Located at the northwestern portion of the province the place is a very beautiful body of land and sea. The place is a natural harbor that was used by the Spanish navy to build and repair and galleons during the 17th century. The place has a very beautiful view of the surrounding islands and sea.              </l1>
 
 </description>

 </viewdeck>

 <paadjaofalls>
 
 <title>paadjao falls</title>

 <description><l1>The Paadjao Falls are located in Bocboc, Mogpog, Marinduque. They are a series of gently cascading falls that settles into a 15-foot fall. Hunt for nature- formed bathtubs downstream and enjoy Jacuzzi-like effect. It is an ideal place for picnicking or camping. Paadjao Falls is an ideal place for family picnics and camping.              </l1>
 
 </description>

 </paadjaofalls>

 <balanacancove>
 
 <title>balanacan cove</title>

 <description><l1> This is one of the most ideal and secluded cove of the province that witnessed the long history of Marinduque. This location was chosen by the Spanish Admiralty as construction and repair facility of the Spanish navy. The galleon “San Juan de Bautista” and almirante “San Marcos”were made in this cove. During the closing of WWII, on November 25, 1944, two of the four Imperial Japanese Navy warships camouflaging in the cove were sunk by the American dive bombers form the USS Intrepid and killing thousands of Japanese. Two Jap shipwrecks still lays done under 140 feet of water for advanced wreck divers to explore.               </l1>

 </description>

 </balanacancove>

 <ulongbeach>
 
 <title>ulong beach</title>

 <description><l1>  Ulong Beach is found on the Island of Marinduque, the Heart of the Philippines.  Located in Municipality of Mogpog and the Barangay of Capayang, the beach faces to the west with views of Mindoro and Batangas.  Our lot presently contains three open seating structures and a fresh water well.  The lot is fenced for privacy. It is the perfect place to spend the day with the family.  Calm shallow water makes it the perfect place to swim with the children.            </l1>

 </description>

 </ulongbeach>

</mogpog>

<boac>
<title>BOAC</title>
 
 <welcome>WELCOME AND VISIT BOAC !!!</welcome>

 <boacchurch>

 <title>boac church</title>

 <description><l1> The church was constructed facing east with its rear overlooking the lower town, called labak by the natives, in 1756. It was seen to serve as a refuge of the townspeople against pirate attacks prevalent in the era, in addition to its purpose as a place for worship when it was finally built in 1792.             </l1>
 
 </description>

 </boacchurch>

  <buliasninbeach>

 <title>buliasnin beach</title>

 <description><l1> Buliasnin is a barangay in the municipality of Boac, in the province of Marinduque. Its population as determined by the 2020 Census was 1,457. This represented 2.54% of the total population of Boac.             </l1>
 
 </description>

 </buliasninbeach>

  <laylayport>

 <title>laylay port</title>

 <description><l1> This is an old pier in the town of Boac, in the province of Marinduque, Philippines. This place is also used in many events. Like concert, Birthday parties, and etc.             </l1>
 
 </description>

 </laylayport>

  <boacmuseum>

 <title>boac museum</title>

 <description><l1> The branch museum is housed in an old Spanish building that used to be a library and Municipal Trial Court of Boac, Marinduque. Representative and now Governor Carmencita Reyes, who facilitated the restoration of the building and construction of showcases, made possible the turnover of the lot and building to the National Museum by the municipality of Boac. The museum measures 410 square meters including the mezzanine floor. Boac, dubbed as a small paradise, is the capital town. The Boac branch museum was formally opened to the public on February 22, 1995.   </l1>

</description>

 </boacmuseum>

</boac>

<gasan>
        <title>GASAN</title>
 
 <welcome>WELCOME AND VISIT GASAN !!!</welcome>

 <tresreyesisland>

 <title>tres reyes island</title>

 <description><l1>The Tres Reyes Islands Melchor, Baltazar, and Gaspar (the biggest)  sit off the coast of Gasan in Marinduque. The islands have soft sand and blue waters where you can spend a couple of hours taking photos, swimming, and beach bumming. This destination is an ideal weekend or summer getaway because of its proximity and accessibility from Metro Manila. You don’t have to book a flight because you can go there on a whim via bus and ferry.              </l1></description>

 </tresreyesisland>

 <parishchurch>

 <title>parish church</title>

 <description><l1> The church is called the St, Joseph Parish Church at Poblacion, Gasan.  Records show that it was built sometime in 1609. Thousands of polished coconut shells were made into tiles and carefully placed on the every beams of the church. Gasan is one of the municipalities that comprise the island province of Marinduque.  It is right next to  the municipality of Boac. My trip to Gasan was unforgettable because of this beautiful church again, located on top of a hill, overlooking the vast blue ocean (I don’t know if it’s West Philippine Sea or Pacific Ocean.)Going to the church is a bit of a challenge. You could go either climb the stairs or ride a vehicle all the way to the top.             </l1>
 
 </description>

 </parishchurch>

 <pinkystaha>

 <title>pinkys taha resort</title>

 <description><l1>Pinkys Taha Beach Resort is located in Gasan, Marinduque. Pinkys Taha Beach Resort is working in Sports and recreation, Other accommodation, Public swimming pools, Holiday homes, cabins and resorts activities.   </l1>
 
 </description>

 </pinkystaha>

  <gasparisland>

 <title>gaspar island</title>

 <description><l1>Gaspar Island is a great place to go swimming, snorkeling, and beach bumming in. Lay on the sand for sunbathing and douse the heat in its clear cool waters. Gaspar Island, known as the largest among the three islands in Gasan collectively called Tres Reyes Islands, got its name from the biblical three kings who presented gifts to the newborn Jesus in Bethlehem. Spanning approximately 108 hectares, the island was originally called "Laki," meaning big. Situated in Barangay Pinggan, Gasan, Marinduque, the Tres Reyes Islands, also referred to as the "Three Kings," form a chain of three islands located off the coast of Gasan.  </l1>
 
 </description>

 </gasparisland>

</gasan>

<buenavista>
        <title>BUENAVISTA</title>
 
 <welcome>WELCOME AND VISIT BUENAVISTA !!!</welcome>

 <haynonhills>

 <title>haynon hills</title>

 <description><l1> This rolling hills on the lower slopes of Balagbag mountain range and on the upper parts of Bagtingon and Malbog usually during the dry months turn brown due to the green grasses that abound the area turns dry. This rolling hills are composed of Tertiary Period Upper Miocene epoch and classified as Gasan Formation made largely of tuff and tuffaceous clastics that was formed around 11.6 to 5.33 million years ago.             </l1></description>

 </haynonhills>

 <hotspring>

 <title>hot spring</title>

 <description><l1> Located in Brgy. Malbog in Buenavista is a quaint spa resort called the Marinduque Hot Springs Resort, once known as Susana Hot Spring. This part of Marinduque is blessed with its supply of natural hot spring waters like those hot spring resorts in Pansol Laguna, but not too commercialized. </l1>
 
 </description>

 </hotspring>

 <elephantisland>

 <title>elephant island</title>

 <description><l1> Bellarocca Island Resort and Spa in Marinduque is distinct from the other upscale, luxury resorts of its category anywhere in the country. All 20 hectares of Bellarocca Island Resort and Spa is mountainous terrain, with its highest point at 114 meters above sea-level. To many seasoned travellers, the images of the picturesque island of Santorini in Greece come to mind upon approaching the resort. Common to both are its rolling terrain and immaculate white buildings perched atop its cliffs: white structures that reflect the sun and contrast with the azure blue sea below. Bellarocca Island Resort and Spa is located on a small mountain island of the southern coast of Marinduque.   </l1>
 
 </description>

 </elephantisland>

 <mtmalindig>

 <title>mt malindig</title>

 <description><l1>The tale told by the people of Buenavista, the town that sits at the foot of Malindig, is that during the Spanish times, a Spanish soldier got lost. He came upon a girl sitting down sorting rice. He asked her what was the name of this place. She replied in Tagalog matindig (translation: "Let me stand up") so she could get a better view of the area. The Spaniard mistook the girl and thought the mountain was called Matindig, and unable to enunciate Tagalog, he called it Malindig. </l1>
 
 </description>

 </mtmalindig>

</buenavista>

<torrijos>

 <title>TORRIJOS</title>
 
 <welcome>WELCOME AND VISIT TORRIJOS !!!</welcome>

 <poctoybeach>

 <title>poctoy beach</title>

 <description><l1>   Poctoy White Beach, located in the coastal town of Torrijos in Marinduque, is one of the popular beaches in the Philippines. The beach features a kilometer stretch of fine white sand and pristine blue waters that is perfect for swimming and snorkeling. The place also gives a scenic view of Mount Malindig, the highest point in the province that is famous among beginner mountain climbers.            </l1>
 
 </description>

 </poctoybeach>

 <strawberryfarm>

 <title>strawberry farm</title>

 <description><l1> This strawberry farm is located in Sibuyao, Torrijos. Tourists can experience strawberry picking from October to May, farm tour, and do some pasalubong shopping.             </l1>
 
 </description>

 </strawberryfarm>

 <freedompark>

 <title>freedom park</title>

 <description><l1> We’ve done almost half of our travel plans in Marinduque. Still euphoric from attending the Moriones Festival, still full from gorging some local food and tingling sunburn – we came back to town and felt we needed to escape and have some quiet time and just relax. With that extra time on our hands while in Torrijos,  Marinduque and craving for some space and air, we headed to the Freedom Park, which according to the welcome sign was formerly called the Luneta Park of Torrijos.              </l1>
 
 </description>

 </freedompark>

  <pulanglupa>

 <title>pulang lupa</title>

 <description><l1> Located in high in the mountains of Pulang Lupa, this historical park offers a sweeping panoramic view of the eastern seaboard of Marinduque. This shrine just outside of Torrijos town is home to the most famous battle in the Province of Marinduque during the Philippine-American War.</l1>
 
 </description>

 </pulanglupa>

</torrijos>


</marinduque>